African National Congress Collection
© 2005 University of Connecticut
African National Congress Collection.
undated, 1993-1999.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
African National Congress.
.5 linear feet.
MSS19990022
Established in 1912, the African National Congress was created to provide a political avenue for the struggle for equality of Blacks in South Africa. Working in exile from 1960 until 1990, members of the ANC established foreign offices to continue the political work necessary to end apartheid in South Africa. The governing party since 1994, the ANC has established its archives at the University of Fort Hare, an historically Black institution. In March 1999, the ANC and the University of Connecticut signed a Memorandum of Understanding establishing a partnership to foster training, assistance and cooperation.
Scope and Content
The collection contains publications, posters, and ephemeral materials collected by representatives of the University of Connecticut while in South Africa.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Human Rights. See also, the papers of Oliver Tambo and A. B. Xuma, available in microfilm. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
Mandela, Nelson. Long Walk to Freedom. The Autobiography of Nelson Mandela. Randburg, South Africa: Macdonald Purnell, 1994.
South Africa, the imprisoned society. International Defence and Aid Fund for Southern Africa. Svensk (Swedish?) Text.
ANC/UConn singing & memorandum. Dodd Video 176/177 (PAL Dodd Video 178)
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Organizations:
African National Congress.
Subjects:
Anti-apartheid movements--South Africa.; Political parties--South Africa.
Places:
South Africa--Race relations--Political aspects.
Document Types:
Publications.; Newspaper clippings.; Postcards.; Ephemera.
Occupations:
Political party.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The ephemeral materials were donated by University faculty and staff. The microfilm was purchased from the University of the Witwatersrand.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Collection, undated, 1993-1999
  - Clippings, 1999 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Ephemera, undated (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Inside the ANC Archives, undated (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - “A Legend for the Future”, 1998 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Mandela's 80th Birthday, 1998 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Maz'enethole! Exhibit Catalogue, 1997 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Memorandum of Understanding, 1999 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Nobel Peace Prize publication, 1993 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Postcards, undated (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - University of Fort Hare, 1998 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - ANC flag (small), undated (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - Robben Island Quarry Rock, undated (Box 1:, Folder 12)
- Microfilm
  - A. B. Xuma Papers, ca. 1939-1949, 7 rolls of microfilm
  - O.R. Tambo Papers, University of the Witwatersrand, undated, 19 rolls of microfilm